laughing. CHAPTER 23 MAGIC Dr. Craven had been waiting some
time at the house when they returned to it. He had indeed begun to wonder if it
might not be wise to send someone out to explore the garden
paths. When Colin was brought back to his room the poor man looked him over
seriously. "You should not have stayed so long," he said. "You must not overexert
yourself." "I am not tired at all," said Colin. "It has made me well tomorrow I am
going out in the morning morning as well as in the
afternoon." "I am not sure that I can allow it," answered Dr.
Craven. "I am afraid it would not be wise." "It would not be wise to try to stop
me," said Colin quite seriously. "I am going." Even Mary had found out that one
of Collin's chief peculiarities was that he did not know in the least what a rude
little brute he was with his way of ordering people
about. He had lived on a sort of desert island all his life and as he had been
the king of it he had made his own manners and had had no one to compare
himself with. Mary had indeed been rather like him herself and since she had been
at mlwa had gradually discovered that her own manners had not been of the kind
which is usual or popular. Having made this discovery she
naturally thought it of enough interest to communicate to Colin. So she sat and looked at him
curiously for a few minutes after Dr.
Craven had gone. She wanted to make him ask her why
she was doing it and of course she did.
"What are you looking at me for?" he said.
"I'm thinking that I am rather sorry for Dr. Craven." "So am I," said Colin calmly, but
not without an air of some satisfaction.
"He won't get mistle at all now I'm not going to
die." "I'm sorry for him because of that, of course," said Mary, "but I was thinking just
then that it must have been very horrid to have had to be polite for 10 years to
a boy who was always rude. I would never have done it." "Am I rude?" Colin inquired
undisturbedly. "If you had been his own boy and he had been a slapping sort of
man," said Mary, "he would have slapped you."
"But he Daren said Colin. "No, he Daren answered Mistress Mary, thinking the
thing out quite without prejudice. "Nobody ever dared to do
anything you didn't like— —because you were going to die in things like that.
You were such a poor thing." "But," announced Colin stubbornly, "I am not going to be a poor
thing. I won't let people think I'm one. I stood on my feet this
afternoon." "It is always having your own way that has made you so queer," Mary went
on, thinking aloud. Colin turned his head, frowning. "Am I queer?" he
demanded. "Yes," answered Mary, "very. But you need be cross," she added impartially,
"because so am I queer— —and so is Ben Weatherstaff. But I am not as queer as I
was before I began to like people and before I found the
garden." "I don't want to be queer," said Colin. "I am not going to be," and he
frowned again with determination. He was a very proud boy. He lay thinking for a while and then
Mary saw his beautiful smile begin and gradually change his whole face. "I shall
stop being queer," he said, "if I go every day to the garden. There is Magic in there—
—good Magic, you know, Mary. I am sure there
is." "So am I," said Mary. "Even if it isn't real Magic," Colin said, "we can pretend it
is. Something is there— something "It's Magic," said Mary, "but not black. It's as white as
snow." They always called it Magic and indeed it seemed like it in the months
that followed— —the wonderful months— —the radiant months— —the amazing
ones. Oh! the things which happened in that garden! If you have never had a garden,
you cannot understand, and if you have had a garden you will know that it would
take a whole book to describe all that came to pass there. At first it seemed that green
things would never cease pushing their way through the earth, in the grass, in
the beds, even in the crev of the walls. Then the green things began to
show buds and the buds began to unfurl and show color, every shade of blue, every
shade of purple, every tint and hue of crimson. In its happy days flowers had
been tucked away into every inch and hole and corner. Ben Weatherstaff had seen it done
and had himself scraped out mortar from between the bricks of the wall and made
pockets of earth for lovely clinging things to grow on. Iris and white Lies rose out of the
grass in sheaves, and the green alcoves filled themselves with amazing armies of
the blue and white flower lances of tall delphiniums or colines or
campanulas. "She was main fond of them— —she was," Ben weather staff said. "She liked
them things as was all as pointing up to the blue sky, she used to tell.
Not as she was one of them as looked down on the earth— —not her. She just loved
it but she said as the blue sky allus look so joyful." The seeds Dickon and Mary had
planted grew as if fairies had tended them. Satiny poppies of all tints danced
in the breeze by the score gay defying flowers which had lived in the garden
for years and which it might be confessed seemed rather to wonder how
such new people had got there. And the roses— —the roses! Rising out of the grass, tangled
round the Su dial wreathing the tree trunks and hanging from their branches,
climbing up the walls and spreading over them with long garlands falling in
cascades— —they came alive day by day, hour by hour. Fair fresh leaves, and buds— —and
buds— —tiny at first but swelling and working Magic until they burst and uncurled into cups of
scent delicately spilling themselves over their brims and filling the garden
air. Colin saw it all, watching each change as it took place. Every morning he
was brought out and every hour of each day when it didn't rain he spent in the
garden. Even gray days pleased him. He would lie on the grass "watching things growing," he
said. If you watched long enough, he declared, you could see buds un sheath
themselves. Also you could make the acquaintance of strange busy insect
things running about on various unknown but evidently serious
errands, sometimes carrying tiny scraps of straw or feather or food, or climbing
blades of grass as if they were trees from whose tops one could look out to
explore the country. A mole throwing up its mound at the end of its burrow and
making its way out at last with the long nailed paws which looked so like elfish
hands, had absorbed him one whole morning.
Ants' ways Beatles ways, bees' ways, frogs' ways Bird's ways, plants' ways, gave him a
new world to explore and when Dickon revealed them all and added Fox's ways
Otter's way ways ferret's ways, squirrels' ways, and trouts and water rats and
Badger ways, there was no end to the things to talk about and think
over. And this was not the half of the Magic. The fact that he had really once
stood on his feet had set Colin thinking tremendously and when Mary told him of
the spell she had worked he was excited and approved of it greatly.
He talked of it constantly. "Of course there must be lots
of Magic in the world," he said wisely one day, "but people don't know what it is
like or how to make it. Perhaps the beginning is just to say
nice things are going to happen until you make them happen. I am going to try and
experiment." The next morning when they went to the secret garden he sent at
once for Ben weather staff Ben came as quickly as he could and
found the Raja standing on his feet under a tree and looking very grand but
also very beautifully smiling. "Good morning, Ben weather staff
he said. "I want you and Dickon and Miss
Mary to stand in a row and listen to me because I am going to tell you something
very important I I sir!" answered Ben Weatherstaff, touching his
forehead. (One of the long concealed charms of Ben Weatherstaff was that in
his boyhood he had once run away to sea and had made voyages. So he could reply
like a sailor.) "I am going to try a scientific experiment," explained the Raja
When I grow up I am going to make great scientific discoveries and I am going to
begin now with this experiment I I sir!" said Ben weather
staff promptly, though this was the first time he had heard of great scientific
discoveries. It was the first time Mary had heard of them, either, but even at
this stage she had begun to realize that, queer as he was, Colin had read about a
great many singular things and was somehow a very convincing sort of boy.
When he held up his head and fixed his strange eyes on you it seemed as if you
believed him almost in spite of yourself though he was only 10 years old— —going on
11 At this moment he was especially convincing because he suddenly felt the
fascination of actually making a sort of speech like a grown-up
person. "The great scientific discoveries I'm going to make," he went on, "will be
about Magic. Magic is a great thing and scarcely anyone knows anything about it
except a few people in old books— —and Mary a little, because she was born in
India where there are fake ears I believe Dickon knows some Magic, but
perhaps he doesn't know he knows it. He charms animals and
people. I would never have let him come to see me if he had not been an animal
charmer— —which is a boy charmer, too, because a boy is an animal I'm sure
there is Magic in everything, only we have not sense enough to get hold of it
and make it do things for us— —like electricity and horses and
steam." This sounded so imposing that Ben weather staff became quite excited and
really could not keep still I I sir," he said and he began to stand up quite
straight. "When Mary found this garden it looked quite dead," the oror
proceeded. "Then something began pushing things up out of the soil and making
things out of nothing.
One day things weren't there and another they were. I had never watched things
before and it made me feel very curious. Scientific people are always
curious and I'm going to be scientific. I keep saying to myself, 'What is it? What is
it?' It's something. It can't be nothing! I don't know its name so I call it
Magic. I have never seen the sunrise but Mary and Dickon have and from what they
tell me I am sure that is Magic too.
Something pushes it up and draws it.
Sometimes since I've been in the garden I've looked up through the trees at the
sky and I have had a strange feeling of being happy as if something were pushing
and drawing in my chest and making me breathe fast. Magic is always pushing and
drawing and making things out of nothing. Everything is made out of Magic,
leaves and trees, flowers and birds, badgers and foxes and squirrels and
people. So it must be all around us. In this garden— —in all the
places. The Magic in this garden has made me stand up and know I am going to live
to be a man. I am going to make the scientific
experiment of trying to get some and put it in myself and make it push and draw
me and make me strong. I don't know how to do it
but I think that if you keep thinking about it and calling it perhaps it will
come. Perhaps that is the first baby way to get
it. When I was going to try to stand that first time Mary kept saying to herself
as fast as she could, 'You can do it! You
can do it!' and I did. I had to try myself
at the same time, of course, but her Magic helped me— —and so did Dickens Every
morning and evening and as often of in the daytime as I can remember I am going
to say, 'Magic is in me! Magic is making me
well! I am going to be as strong as Dickon, as strong as Dickon!' And you must
all do it, too. That is my experiment. Will you help, Ben weather
staff I I sir!" said Ben weather staff I I If you keep doing it every day as
regularly as soldiers go through drill we shall see what will happen and find
out if the experiment succeeds. You learn things by saying them over and over and
thinking about them until they stay in your mind forever and I think it will be
the same with Magic. If you keep calling it to come to you and help you it will
get to be part of you and it will stay and do
things." "I once heard an officer in India tell my mother that there were fakers
who said words over and over thousands of times," said Mary. "I've heard jeem
falworth wife say the same thing over thousands of times calling gem a drunken
brute," said Ben weather staff dryly Summit olis come of that, sure enough. He
gave her a good hiding and went to the Blue Lion and got as drunk as a
lord." Colin drew his brows together and thought a few minutes. Then he cheered up.
"Well," he said, "you see something did come of it. She used the wrong Magic until she
made him beat her.
If she'd used the right Magic and had said something nice perhaps he wouldn't
have got as drunk as a lord and perhaps— —perhaps he might have bought her a new
bonnet." Ben Weatherstaff chuckled and there was shrewd admiration in his
little old eyes that a clever lad as well as a straight-legged one Mr Colin,"
he said. "Next time I see best falworth I'll give her a bit of a hint of what
Magic will do for her. She'd be rare and pleased pleased if the ctif experiment
worked and so you'd Jam Dickon had stood listening to the lecture, his round eyes
shining with curious delight. Nut and Shell were on his shoulders and he held
a long-eared white rabbit in his arm and stroked and stroked it softly while it
laid its ears along its back and enjoyed itself. "Do you think the experiment will
work?" Colin asked him, wondering what he was thinking.
He so often wondered what Dickon was thinking when he saw him looking at him
or at one of his "creatures" with his happy wide smile. He smiled now and his
smile was wider than usual I he answered, "that I do. It'll work same as the seeds
do when the sun shines on them It'll work for sure. Shall us begin it now?"
Colin was delighted and so was Mary.
Fired by recollection of fakers and devotees in illustrations Colin
suggested that they should all sit cross-legged under the tree which made a
canopy. "It will be like sitting in a sort of temple," said Colin. "I'm rather tired
and I want to sit down a said Dickon thou mustn't begin by saying thou tired
thou might spoil the Magic." Colin turned and looked at him— —into his innocent round
eyes. "That's true," he said slowly.
"I must only think of the Magic." It all seemed most majestic and mysterious when
they sat down in their circle. Ben weatherstar felt as if he had
somehow been led into appearing at a prayer meeting Ordinarily he was very
fixed in being what he called Asian prayer meetings but this being the Raj's
affair he did not resent it and was indeed inclined to be gratified at being called upon to
assist. Mistress Mary felt solemnly enraptured. Dickon held his rabbit in his
arm, and perhaps he made some Charmers signal no one heard, for when he sat down,
cross-legged like the rest, the crow, the fox, the squirrels and the lamb slowly
drew near and made part of the circle, settling each into a place of rest as if
of their own desire. "The 'creatures' have come," said Colin gravely the They want to help
us." Colin really looked quite beautiful, Mary thought. He held his head high as if
he felt like a sort of priest and his strange eyes had a wonderful look in
them. The light shone on him through the tree canopy. "Now we will begin," he said. "Shall
we sway backward and forward, Mary, as if we were dervishes?" "I Cann of do no swaying
backward and forward said benw the stuff I've got the
rheumatics." "The Magic will take them away," said Colin in a High Priest tone, "but we
won't sway until it has done it. We will only
chant." "I can of do no chanting said Ben weather staff a trifle testily. "They
turned me out of the church choir the only time I ever tried it." No one smiled.
They were all too much in earnest.
Colin's face was not even crossed by a shadow. He was thinking only of the
Magic. "Then I will chant," he said. And he began, looking like a strange boy spirit.
"The sun is shining— —the sun is shining.
That is the Magic. The flowers are growing— —the roots are stirring. That is
the Magic. Being alive is the Magic— —being strong is the Magic. The Magic is in me—
—the Magic is in me. It is in me— —it is in
me. It's in every one of us. It's in Ben weather staff's back. Magic! Magic! Come
and help!" He said it a great many times— —not a thousand times but quite a goodly
number. Mary listened entranced. She felt as if it were at once queer and
beautiful and she wanted him to go on and on. Ben Weatherstaff began to feel
soothed into a sort of dream which was quite agreeable. The humming of the bees in the
blossoms mingled with the chanting voice and drowsily melted into a
doze Dickens sat cross-legged with his rabbit asleep on his arm and a hand
resting on the lamb's back. Soot had pushed away a squirrel and huddled close
to him on his shoulder, the gray film dropped over his eyes. At last Colin
stopped. "Now I am going to walk around the garden," he announced. Ben
Weatherstaff's head had just dropped forward and he lifted it with a jerk.
"You have been asleep," said Colin now of the sort," mumbled Ben the sermon was good
enough but I'm bound to get out aord the collection." He was not quite awake
yet. "You're not in church," said Colin. "Not me," said Ben, straightening
himself. "Who said I were? I heard every bit of it. You said the Magic was in my
back the doctor calls it rheumatics." The Raja waved his hand. "That
was the wrong Magic," he said. "You will get better. You have my permission to go to
your work. But come back tomorrow I'd like to see thee walk
around the garden," grunted Ben. It was not an unfriendly grunt, but it was a grunt.
In fact, being a stubborn old party and not having entire faith in Magic he had
made up his mind that if he was sent away he would climb his ladder and look
over the wall so that he might be ready to hobble back if there were any
stumbling. The rajer did not object to his staying and so the procession was
formed. It really did look like a procession. Colin was at its head with
Dickon on one side and Mary on the other.
Ben weather staff walked behind, and the "creatures" trailed after them, the lamb
and the fox cub keeping close to Dickon, the white rabbit hopping along or
stopping to nibble and Su following with the solemnity of a person who felt
himself in charge. It was a procession which moved slowly but with dignity.
Every few yards it stopped to rest. Colin leaned on Dickon's arm and privately Ben
Weatherstaff kept a sharp lookout, but now and then Colin took his hand from
its support and walked a few steps alone.
His head was held up all the time and he looked very
grand. "The Magic is in me!" he kept saying.
"The Magic is making me strong! I can feel it! I can feel
it!" It seemed very certain that something was upholding and uplifting him. He sat
on the seats in the alcoves, and once or twice he sat down on the grass and
several times he paused in the path and leaned on Dickon, but he would not give
up until he had gone all around the garden. When he returned to the canopy
tree his cheeks were flushed and he looked triumphant. "I did it! The Magic worked!" he
cried. "That is my first scientific discovery." "What will Dr. Craven say?" broke
out Mary. "He won't say anything," Colin answered, "because he will not be told.
This is to be the biggest secret of all.
No one is to know anything about it until I have grown so strong that I can
walk and run like any other boy. I shall come here every day in my chair and I
shall be taken back in it. I won't have people whispering and asking questions
and I won't let my father hear about it until the experiment has quite
succeeded. Then sometime when he comes back to mwe I shall just walk into his
study and say 'Here I am; I am like any
other boy. I am quite well and I shall
live to be a man. It has been done by a scientific
experiment.'" "He will think he is in a dream," cried Mary. "He won't believe his
eyes." Colin flushed triumphantly. He had made himself believe
that he was going to get well, which was really more than half the battle, if he
had been aware of it. And the thought which stimulated him more than any other
was this imagining what his father would look like when he saw that he had a son
who was as straight and strong as other father's sons. One of his darkest miseries in the
unhealthy morbid past days had been his hatred of being a sickly weak-backed boy
whose father was afraid to look at him HEK be obliged to believe them," he said.
"One of the things I am going to do, after the Magic works and before I begin to
make scientific discoveries, is to be an athlete." "We shall have thee take to
boxing in a week or so," said Ben weather staff th end with winning the Belt and
being champion prize fighter of all England." Colin fixed his eyes on him
sternly weather staff he said, "that is disrespectful. You must not take
liberties because you are in the secret. However much the Magic works I
shall not be a prize fighter I shall be a Scientific Discoverer ask pardon ask pardon, sir,"
answered Ben, touching his forehead in salute. "I ought to have seed it wasn't a joke in
matter," but his eyes twinkled and secretly he was immensely
pleased. He really did not mind being snubbed since the snubbing meant that
the lad was gaining strength and spirit